Fine.
Imagine that you develop a software
application that use AI agent, and there
are more than one, and you need to have
a way to orchestrate those AI agents.
Now, each agent produce output
which is not deterministic.
So how can we orchestrate AI
agents when we actually can't use a
simple if or a simple switch case?
One of the way is to use pattern matching,
and this is the topic of this session.
My name is Haim Hakel.
I live in Tel Aviv.
I'm a self-learner for many years.
I'm a lecturer in university for
more than twenty-five years, teaching
advanced topics in computer science.
Before that, I was a lecturer in the
university for macroeconomics courses.
These are the domains I find
interesting, and spec-driven
development with AI is my favorite.
I wrote books in Hebrew.
I wrote books in English I develop
courses in Hebrew, courses in English.
I have a true passion to build, and
if you check these ventures, these
are the ventures currently my company,
Zill Dell Technologies, is working on.
So we develop multiple ventures, and
when I said we, I meant me and the
AI agents, but this is another story.
I organize conferences.
I have a meetup group where we meet
once a month or even more than that.
I build communities.
I publish newsletters.
Free to subscribe.
You can find them on
the LinkedIn platform.
And this is my company structure.
More info about what I'm
doing you can find in my blog.
Check blog.lifemichael.com.
So let's start.
Let's start with pattern matching
and later move forward and see how
can we use pattern matching when
orchestrating our use of AI agents.
So pattern matching is a
switch case on steroids.
This is the common perception.
However, it is by far more than that.
Pattern matching is supported
in many programming languages.
Java is just one of them.
Now, the code samples
I created are in Java.
You can easily do the same or similar
with other programming languages.
So let's take a look at this code sample.
So in this code sample, what we
have is simple switch expression.
Now, that switch expression actually
takes the reference for an object,
and then using these cases, check
the type Of that object compared
with these types that are mentioned.
Not… Now, when a match takes
place, then the reference that
animalOld will be assigned to the
variable next to that specific type
that has a match with our object.
And then not only that, that specific
variable, it can be dog, tiger, cat,
depends on the type of the object, is
assigned with a reference to that object.
Each of these variables, its type
is the type that has a match.
So we can invoke functions
defined in that type.
So for instance, in this code sample,
we create an object from dog, the
class Dog, and then we call hello.
Hello returns a string.
Hello take the reference to the object
we had, we have, the dog object, and then
compare the type to each of these options.
Now, a match takes place
in line 10 in this case.
So the variable dog is now assigned
with the same reference that animalOld,
just that the type of the variable
dog is not animal, it is dog.
So we can call the ow function
that was defined for the dog class.
So if you see, if I execute,
here is the expected output.
We get ow.
Now We could do it a bit different.
We could instead of having a switch
expression that just check the type,
it could be something else, and we
are going to see the possibilities.
But first, let's start with
something simple, comparing the type
Next, there is a requirement for
completeness you should be aware of.
Now, what does it mean?
It means that you must cover all
options in your switch expression.
For instance, in this case, we know
that the variable animal hold a
reference of the type animal, but
it is a reference to an object that
was instantiated either from dog,
cat, and tiger, and this is because
animal was defined as a sealed type.
Sealed type meaning that over
here we specify which are the
types that can extend animal.
So once we specify just these
three types, it means that we
actually cover all options.
Now, if animal wasn't
a sealed type, that was
another story.
Look, I will put here a comment,
and I will take sealed away,
and here we have a problem.
And the problem is that the
completeness requirement is not kept.
We don't have completeness because
now when we call hello and pass over
a reference of the type animal for an
object, it can be an object of the type
dog or cat or tiger, but who knows?
Maybe it would be an object of another
type that we haven't… we didn't
define, but someone else defined.
So we don't have a full
coverage of all options.
In that case, we can still achieve
the completeness requirement by
adding a case that refer null
and default, as you can see.
But this is also the motivation
for using sealed type.
As you can see, when using sealed
type, we actually limit the
options, limits the possibilities.
Now, if you think about working with AI
agents, it might be a good approach to
limit the possibilities for output we get.
Either we got an output that means
there is a solution, the AI agent
succeeded, or there is an output
saying the AI failed, or there is
an output saying there is an error.
Three options, for instance.
It could be more
So the completeness requirement is
something you should be aware of,
pay attention to, and in order to
achieve it, highly recommend… It is
highly recommended to use the sealed
keyword so that you can specify which
are the types that can extend the
specific type you are handling, in
this case, a animal, for instance Now
let's talk about guarded patterns.
When using a pattern,
we can add a condition.
So let's take a look at
the code sample itself
Here is a simple code sample.
So we have a switch expression, and
there is a number, value old, or
to be more accurate, on the right,
we have a value of the type int.
And actually what happens here is
auto boxing and value is assigned
with reference to an object of the
type integer that wraps fifteen.
Now, here we have a switch expression,
and we can have multiple cases.
In this case, we have ju- just
two cases, but the first case will
take place if N is bigger than ten.
Now, if the f- the ca- first
case doesn't match, then it
move forward to the other cases.
In this code sample, if I
execute, I expect to get a large
integer being assigned to result
and then printed over here.
Let's see that in action
Large integer.
But we could easily add more cases.
We could say if it's bigger than 100,
then the message will be very large
integer, and if it is just bigger than
10, it would be large integer only.
So now if I change it to a bigger number
and execute it one more time, as you
can see, we got very large integer.
So we can add cases.
We can actually use that additional
condition, the guarded condition, to take
the chaos and turn it into something that
is more deterministic Let's go back to the
slides Now I want to to show you something
that is known as record deconstruction.
Record is actually a way to define
a very simple class mainly for
creating objects that represent data.
That's all.
And here in this case
we have the record point
Now, when you define a new type
using record, you automatically
get auto-generated for you
various methods such as equals to
string, a constructor, and so on.
Now, over here, you specify the parameters
of the constructor of that record.
Record is just like any other type, but
it is also the names of the instance
variables that we will find in every
object instantiated from the type point.
So over here we have pattern matching
that compares the object that was
instantiated from point with in
this case, we have only one case.
So what happens is that the object is
matched with c- the first case because
the first case re-refer the type point
and the object is of the type point.
And then the values inside X and Y,
the two variables the object has,
are extracted into these two local
variables, X and Y, and then we
use them, do something with them.
Now, in this case, the com-
the completeness requirement
is achieved using default.
Let's execute the code, and as
expected, we got the values that
inside X and Y extracted outsi-
outside in this deconstruction
that took place in line eleven.
So that happens a lot when
orchestrating AI agents using pattern
matching, and we will see that
Now, one small feature I want you to be
aware of, if we don't need the variable
that holds the reference to the object
that has a match with a specific case,
then we can just place underscore.
Let's take a look in this case.
So we have a switch expression,
and data is assigned with whatever
was passed over to testType.
Now, as you can see, we don't
have a variable here, over
here, because we don't use it.
And what comes next, right after
the arrow, is something very simple.
We don't use the object that was
matched with this case, so we don't
need the reference for that object, so
we can just place underscore, unlike
what we did in the first code samples.
In the first code samples over here,
for instance, the reference for the
object that was matched with that
specific case was needed because
we needed to invoke a method, so
we didn't place just underscore.
We placed a name for the local variable
to be assigned with the reference to the
object that match this specific case.
So just be aware we can use underscore.
It contributes to the code to become
cleaner, simpler to maintain, worth
to be aware of this option Let's
see how can we use pattern matching
when orchestrating AI agents.
Let's take a look at this code sample.
In this code sample, we have an AI
agent that we created over here.
This is the prompt we pass over,
and the returned value when
calling chat on that AI agent is an
object of the type AgentRawResult.
Now, the method to AgentResult
that was defined in AgentRawResult
returns one of three options.
Either to AgentResult return an
object of the type AgentResult.Answer,
or AgentResult.Clarification,
or AgentResult.Error.
These are the three options.
Now, if you check AgentResult,
it is a sealed type, and the only
types that extend that seal types,
sealed type are nested types that
were defined within the AgentResult.
So we have AgentResult.Answer,
AgentResult.Clarification,
and AgentResult.Error.
These are the three types.
Now, here you can see that When we
call two agent result, the variable
result of the agent result type is
actually assigned with a reference to
an object of one of these three types.
And then Calling The method handle,
passing over the reference to the object,
an object of the type AgentResult.Answer
or AgentResult.Clarification
or AgentResult.Error.
What happens here inside handle is a
simple pattern matching And if everything
goes well, then we can expect the first
case to match, and then we can expect
that answer will re- will return a string
that starts with the word answer, and
right after that, the text that we get
when referring that agentResult.answer
object and calling text method on it.
Now, if you look at the agent
result, then you can see that it
was rec-- defined as a record.
Having text defined over here as kind
of the parameter of answer is also
actually the name of the instance
variable, and in order to get that
value, we call the text method, and
this is exactly what happens over here.
And then we expect eventually, if
everything goes well, that there will
be a match with the first case, and the
output will start with the word answer,
and right after that the text that
the agentResult.answer object holds.
So let's execute this code sample
And just as expected.
Great.
Okay, let's move forward
to the next sample.
In, in this sample, we have a
pipeline of three AI agents, a
planner, a coder, and a reviewer.
And if you check
This code sample, then you can see that
in the beginning, before anything else
over here, we create those three agents.
Now, you can also see that an object
that represents a request is an
object of a type A-A AgentMessage.
This is an object that describes a
message sent from one ag-agent to another.
An AgentMessage, as you can see, it's
an interface but it is also a sealed
interface, and actually it will be
an object of one of these four types.
So over here, you can see a use
of pattern matching in order to
identify the exact type of current,
and based of that, based on that one
of these four strings will be used.
You can also see that in this demo
we have the function step that is
invoked again and again i-- because
the… we have a loop over here and
that loop will continue until finally
current is of the type FinalResult.
So as long as we don't have current
assigned with reference to an object of
the type FinalResult this loop continues.
But the moment that happens, then
we have a match with the last case.
But you can also see that we have a
call to the step function, and whenever
a step is invoked, it takes th-the
three AI agents, as well as the object
that represent the current message,
which is one of these four options.
And step act…
is actually invoked again and again and
through step, whenever a step is invoked,
then using pattern matching we identify
for what purpose step was invoked and then
call the right method on the, on, on the
em, on the required, on, on the AI agent
that should handle that message, either
the planner or the coder or the reviewer.
And then what it returns is being
used to create the next message
that will be passed over i- the next
time this step function is invoked.
So in the beginning when step is invoked,
then the type of, of the argument
that is being passed over to step is
plan request in the beginning, the
first time step is invoked, and then
we have a match with the first case.
And then through deconstruction,
we deconstruct the value that plan
request hold, and that value is
actually being sent to the plan method
that is invoked on the plan request
on, on the planner AI agent, sorry.
And what plan returns will be passed
over to the constructor of code request.
The next method that next time step
is invoked will be the current.
So the next time step is invoked, current
will be that code request object, so
we will have a match with this case.
And here, what happens is that
the coder is activated, code is
invoked on the Coder AI agent.
It takes the specification that
was actually generated by the
planner, and then the code that the
function code returns, this is what
is being sent over when the review
request object is instantiated.
So now we know that se- step
returns a re-review request object.
So the next time from this loop
that step will be invoked, step
will take a review request object.
So we will have a match with this case.
And now when the reviewer AI agent does
its job and review the code and returns
something, that something is being passed
over to the constructor of final result.
And now finally, step returns
a final result object.
So the next time this is
checked, then we have true.
So not when you invoke it
on true, you get false.
Loop ends, and we continue
to the end of the program.
So let's execute this demo for a pipeline.
And
here you can see that eventually
We will get the output of the
code itself and the output of the
reviewer AI agent does its work.
So this is a pipeline.
It's not straightforward to understand
just from my short overview.
My recommendation is to take the code
and execute it on your end with a
debugger, go over it step by step,
and then pay attention to the use I'm
doing with the pattern matching i- in
each and every step of the execution
Let's take a look at this code sample.
Here, in this code sample, we have the
router orchestrator class where you can
find code that creates a router agent,
translator agent, and a summarizer agent.
Now, over here, you can see that we
have a loop that goes over all strings
in the array inputs, and then each
iteration, the focus on, is on a specific
string, and this is the string that
will be passed over to the router agent.
Now, the router agent
As you can see over here
Is the one that will handle dispatching
the handling of that prompt it
received to the most appropriate agent.
And there are two options.
There is the translator and the
one… There is the summarizer.
So if you check dispatch Over here,
then you can see that we have a
pattern matching that compares the task
classification object with two options,
translate task and summarize tasks.
Now, task classification, if you
check it over here, is a sealed type.
So when you have a task classification
object, either it is a translate task
object or a summarize task object.
So back to the code.
Using this pattern matching, either
we have a match with the first case
or the second case, and in according
to that, either that prompt will
be passed over to the translator AI
agent or to the summarizer AI agent.
And then dispatch will return
the string that will eventually
be assigned to result.
And here you can see another
use of pattern matching, just
for getting the name of the AI
agent that handled that prompt.
And then we have an output that includes
the agent name, the text result, and
the result that was returned from
that agent that its name was printed.
So let's execute this code sample
And as you can see
Over here you can see the output
for the first input that was
handled by the translator AI agent
And then there is another Input
Over here, that AI understands
as a request to summarize.
And because of that, it is
handled by the summarizer AI agent
Just as with all other code samples,
my recommendation is to take
the code, debug it step by step.
And if there are topics in Java
that are not familiar with, for
you let's topics such as sealed
type, record, catch up don't wait.
Learn them, and then return
back to these code samples
Let's move forward to
the next code sample.
Over here, we have a demo for using
pattern matching in a loop in which
there is another retry and another retry
limited by a specific number of retries.
So let's look at the code itself
Here, if you look at retry orchestrator,
then you can see that there is
a maximum number of attempts.
This is a common scenario where we
ask the AI agent to do something,
and it fails, and then we ask that AI
agent to try doing it again and again.
But we limit the number of
tries, the number of attempts.
We can't allow a loop to
execute without to stop.
So there is always a limit for
how many attempts there will be
a maximum number of attempts.
So let's take a look at this code sample.
We have over here if you look at the, the
main, then you can see that we have the
coder agent, the reviewer agent, and then
there is a task, write a Java method that
reverts a string using a string builder.
And this is the task that will be
handed over to the coder AI agent first.
Now, if you look over here, when
calling retry loop, passing over
the task, as well as the coder
and the reviewer Read write loop
Text the task and the two agent,
the coder and the reviewer.
So the first thing is asking
the coder to write the code.
Now
we ask the other AI agent, the reviewer
To review the code and it returns a
decision, a review decision object.
Now, if you check review decision
object It is a simple record
And every review decision
object has variables.
Approve, true or false, the
code, the score, the feedback.
So we get a review decision object from
calling the review method on the reviewer
AI agent And we can check whether it was
approved or maybe it wasn't approved.
And then there is the review outcome type.
Now, the review outcome is an interface.
You don't… You c- you can't have an
object instantiated from review outcome.
It is an interface that was created using
the sealed keyword, and there are only
two possible types: approved and rejected.
That's why
When outcome is assigned either with
an approved object or rejected object
We can use pattern matching to handle
that So over here you can see the use of
pattern matching together with a guardrail
With a condition.
So if our review outcome object is
of the type approved and the score
bigger than seven, this will happen.
If it is just of the type
approved, this will happen.
And if it is of the type rejected, then
if we still have the possibility to
attempt another for ano- to-- another
time to attempt again, meaning if the
number of attempts is smaller than
maxAttempts, then there will be another
call to code on the Coder AI agent
to try to code And then in that case
the retry loop function doesn't end
In the first case, the second case,
then it ends and we get the code In the
third case, if the number of attempts
so far is smaller than maxAttempt,
then there will be another attempt
and code will be updated Now eventually
We will get the code back from retry loop.
However, the output
Will be either reviewer approved
with the high score or just review
approved and the score, that's all.
Or we will see orchestrator
re-invoking coder with feedback.
The feedback we got from the reviewer,
we can send it to the coder AI agent.
Maybe now that would, will be better
And if none of these outputs takes
place, then meaning the loop ended
because we didn't have a success and the
number of attempts is bigger than max
attempt, and in that case, we will get
this output, Orchestrator warning max
retries reached, returning last attempt.
And of course, the code will be returned.
So if we look at main Over here
We will get the output orchestrator
final code and the code, but we
will also get a message saying if
the reviewed reviewer approved with
the high score or just approved.
Now let's execute this code sample
So here's the task, and eventually
in all cases we get the code.
But let's take a look at
the messages we got before.
So as you can see we got the
message approved with the
score ten For the first attempt
Meaning we get the message,
"Reviewer approved high score 10."
10 is the highest score Possible.
And the, the rest is the code itself
Great.
So that was a code sample for
using pattern matching for retry
Again and again, as long as the
number of attempts is not bigger
the, than the maximum allowed.
And as you could see, the
differentiation between the two cases
Either approved, and there is the
case in a-- to be approved with
a high score or just approved,
or the other case, rejected.
And the differentiation
between the two cases Is taking
place using pattern matching
Let's take a look at this code
sample where we have three AI agents.
We have the judge agent, and we have
agent A and agent B. The task will be
handled both by agent A and agent B. The
judge agent will pick the best solution.
Let's look at the code itself.
So when we execute the code,
first, we create the agents.
Then this is the task, and then calling
fanout, passing over the task and
the three agents, look what happens
Agent A and agent B start working.
Eventually, we get a
solution from both of them.
We even print it to the screen,
and then we call the fin- the
method judge on our judge AI agent.
Now, judge, as you can see over
here, returns a JudgeVerdict object.
JudgeVer- Verdict is a sealed interface.
The only types that can implement
JudgeVerdict are picked A and
picked B Over here, you can see
these two types define this record.
So back over here, we get a judgeVerdict
object, which is, as you could see, either
an object of the type PickedA or PickedB.
And then calling selectWinner, passing
over the judgeVerdict object and the
two solutions, look what happens.
Using pattern matching, either we have a
match with the first case or the second
case, and accordingly, either selectWinner
returns this string or this string.
So selectWinner returns something,
and this is exactly what fanout
returns, and that is assigned to result
And then we can expect having
this text printed to the screen
together with the result.
And if we look at the output, we
can expect getting to see the string
chosen because right after the solution
and together with the reason, and it
will be actually either solution A or
solution B. So now le-let's execute
this code sample and see how the verdict
eventually translates into output,
where we can see why solution B was
chosen, including the solution B itself.
In that-- in this execution,
in this case, but of course,
things can also be different.
It all depends on the comparison between
solution A and solution B that the judge
agent will handle No These were five
code samples for using pattern matching
When orchestrating AI agents, you can do
nearly the same using other programming
languages that support pattern matching.
It can be C Sharp, Kotlin, Scala Python.
It will look a bit different.
I was using LangChain, but you can use
other libraries for creating AI agents.
Now, the code itself, I created
here a link, so just use that
link for getting the code.
And my recommendation is to execute
those code samples together with the
debugger Step by step, and if you have
questions, of course send me a message.
I will be very glad to assist.
You can find me on LinkedIn, and I will
be very glad to be friends on LinkedIn.
So I wish you good luck, and that's it